ELDIN SAHBAZ

Denver, Colorado, USA +1 (607) 597-9607 | sahbaz.eldin@gmail.com linkedin.com/in/eldinsahbaz | github.com/eldinsahbaz

SUMMARY

Program Manager and Data Scientist with **7+ years of proven success** establishing and scaling transformative, enterprise—level, AI/ML initiatives across the Petroleum and Semiconductor industries. Led the Data Science team's **63**% **market share** in AI developments across British Petroleum's US onshore O&G business and independently produced **US\$997MM** in **value**. Delivered **patent—pending** AI solutions in computational chemistry — **valued at US\$500M+ annually** — for INFICON's Semiconductor business.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Program Manager

British Petroleum (BP)

November 2023 – Present Denver. Colorado

· Directed and executed strategy for BP US onshore Data Science and ML Engineering — achieving 47% market share in Exploration & Development and enabling the team's 63% market share across the division.

- · Managed and deployed the Long-term Production Risk Assessment Simulation tool for Reservoir Engineering.
- · Oversaw the AWS migration for PowerBI reports monitoring the Productivity Index and Saltwater Disposal.

Senior Data Scientist

British Petroleum (BP)

February 2023 – Present Denver. Colorado

- · Generated US\$20MM annually in value for Reservoir Engineering's EOR initiatives delivering the ML Refracturing Estimator and increasing confidence in the Business Unit's Development program by 500%.
- Drove US\$977MM in the Bone Spring formation with a US\$700MM NPV well development plan, US\$250MM D&C, and cutting US\$27MM in core collection launching ML Lithology Recognition.

Data Scientist

INFICON

June 2018 – February 2023 Syracuse, New York

- · Directed the Automated Sensor Calibration development program for semiconductor sensor technologies delivering **patent**—**pending advances** driving annual cost reductions forecasted **in excess of US\$500M**.
- · Invented the Bijective Neural Architecture for density estimation yielding a 95% increase in accuracy.
- · Led efforts defining mathematical foundations for signal processing algorithms and designed A/B tests using SciPy.stats and Nolds delivering a 21% increase in sensor fidelity using SciPy.optimize and Statsmodels.
- · Established KPIs and executed A/B tests with simulated chemical data via PySwarms, SciPy.optimize, SciPy.stats, and SciPy.integrate attaining 50% coverage across chemical detection/monitoring systems.

PATENTS & PUBLICATIONS

Method of Auto Tuning One or More Sensors

USPTO Application 18/686,753

February 2024
Patent Pending

PROFESSIONAL DEVELOPMENT

Core Analysis Workshop

UT Austin Bureau of Economic Geology

April 2024/December 2023

Advanced Power BI — Power Query and DAX $\,$

Havens Consulting

April 2023

Power BI — Reporting and Model Building February 2023 Havens Consulting Machine Learning for Model Predictive Control & Process Analytics June 2019 Dr. S. Joe Qin INVITED PRESENTATIONS Neural Attention for Seismic Data Processing July 2024 BP Geophysics R&D Seminar Improving Mass Spectrometry Signal Fidelity November 2020 INFICON Data Analytics Summit Introduction to AI and Machine Learning November 2020 INFICON Data Analytics Summit Automatic Text Summarization — Deep Learning & Classical Approaches April 2018 Syracuse University iSchool Poster Session **HONORS & AWARDS** Graduate Merit Scholarship August 2017 - May 2018 Syracuse University Summa Cum Laude May 2017 Syracuse University The Warren Semon Prize May 2017 Syracuse University Dean's Leadership Grant September 2014 Syracuse University Dean's List August 2014 – May 2017 Syracuse University The Founders' Scholarship August 2014 – May 2017 Syracuse University

EDUCATION

Syracuse University May 2018

Master of Science | Computer Science

Syracuse University

Bachelor of Science | Computer Science

Summa Cum Laude

SKILLS & COMPETENCIES

Software & Tools AWS SageMaker, Linux, Git, Python, PyTorch, Scikit-learn, Statsmodels, Pandas,

SciPy, NumPy, NLTK, Gensim, OpenCV, Seaborn, Matplotlib, SLB Techlog

Competency Areas AI, Deep Learning, Machine/Statistical Learning, Linear & Nonlinear Modeling, Numerical Optimization, Regression, Classification, Statistics, Probability, Time Series, Statistical Signal Processing, Data Analysis, Data Mining, Agile, CRISP-DM